Xilun Wu

Lawson CS Building, 305 N. University Street, West Lafayette, IN-47907 USA wu636@purdue.edu, https://xilunwu.github.io/, +1 (765)430-2553

RESEARCH INTEREST

Xilun is a sixth-year PhD student in Computer Science at Purdue University. His main research interest sits at exploring the intersection of programming languages and multiple application domains including data management and machine learning. Most of his projects are aimed at bringing high-level language features such as code reuse, abstractions, and modularity to system programming without losing performance with compiler techniques. He is also interested in type theory and category theory.

EDUCATION

• Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA PhD Candidate, Computer Science

2015-Present

• **Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China** BS, Computer Science and Technology

2014

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

• Software Engineer Intern, Facebook, Menlo Park, USA Summer 2019
Involved in the technical design of introducing self-types to Hack language to support Cake Pattern and unify the handling of class, interface, and trait in type checking. Implemented this feature in Hack type checker.

ACADEMY EXPERIENCE

• PhD Candidate, Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA

2015-2020

Has been under supervision of Tiark Rompf as a member of Tiark Rompf research group. Conducted multiple research projects in team. They which include:

- Investigated the practicality of extending the mechanized foundations for Scala and similar languages with full dependent types.
- Implemented a machine learning framework in Scala powered by fusing delimited continuation and multi-staging together.

• Implemented a novel multi-way join algorithm Leapfrog Trie Join (a variation of NPRR).

• Research Assistant, Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA Summer 2018

• Implemented a certain compiler features in the framework of LLVM which primarily are adding optimization annotations/directives in a certain category of high-level programs (grid-based programs in C/C++) to guide the compiler backend to perform auto-parallelization as source-to-source code transformations.

• Research Assistant, Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA 2015-2017

• Implemented a novel multi-way join algorithm Leapfrog Trie Join (a variation of NPRR) and compared it to other state-of-the-art in-memory database systems on TPC-H benchmark.

• Teaching Assistant, Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA 2017-2020

• CS35400 Operating Systems

Fall 2020

• CS52500 Parallel Computing

Spring 2020

• CS35400 Operating Systems

Fall 2019

• CS25200 Systems Programming

June 2017 - May 2019

• CS35200 Compilers: Principles And Practice

Spring 2017

• Master Student, Purdue University, West Lafayette, USA

2014-2015

PAST PROJECTS

- Lantern: an expressive and performant deep learning framework
 - Demystifying differentiable programming: Shift/reset the penultimate backpropagator. **ICFP'19**
 - Backpropagation with Callbacks: Foundations for Efficient and Expressive Differentiable Programming. **NeurIPS'18**
- LMS-NPRR: native query compilation with an efficient NPRR join algorithm implementation in single-core in-memory setting
 - Compiling Graph Queries in Relational Engines. **DBPL'19**
- Extending DOT: investigating the practicality of extending the mechanized foundations for Scala and similar languages with full dependent types
 - Towards Full Dependent Types in DOT/Scala. Poster presentation on PurPL Grad Visit Day 2020.

PRESENTATIONS

- 1. Poster presentation. Towards Full Dependent Types in DOT/Scala. PurPL Grad Visit Day 2020, West Lafayette IN, USA.
- 2. Poster presentation. Backpropagation with Callbacks: Foundations for Efficient and Expressive Differentiable Programming. **NeurIPS'18**, Montreal, Canada.
- 3. Poster presentation. A Language and Compiler View on Differentiable Programming. Huawei Midwest Research Summit 2018, Champaign IL, USA.

AWARDS

• **Distinguished Artifact Award** at OOPSLA 2016 (international conference), Leo Osvald, Grégory Essertel, **Xilun Wu**, Lilliam I. Gonzalez Alayon, Tiark Rompf.

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Fei Wang, Daniel Zheng, James Decker, **Xilun Wu**, Grégory M Essertel, Tiark Rompf. Demystifying differentiable programming: Shift/reset the penultimate backpropagator. ICFP 2019, 31 pages.
- 2. Ruby Tahboub, **Xilun Wu**, Grégory Essertel, Tiark Rompf. Compiling Graph Queries in Relational Engines. DBPL 2019, 12 pages.
- 3. Fei Wang, James Decker, **Xilun Wu**, Grégory Essertel, Tiark Rompf. Backpropagation with Continuation Callbacks: Towards Efficient and Expressive Differentiable Programming. NeurIPS 2018, 12 pages.
- 4. Leo Osvald, Grégory Essertel, **Xilun Wu**, Lilliam I. Gonzalez Alayon, Tiark Rompf. Gentrification gone too far? affordable 2nd-class values for fun and (co-)effect. OOPSLA 2016, 18 page. (**Distinguished Artifact Award**)

TEACHING

Xilun has rich experience in instructing undergrad and graduate level courses in Computer Science. The tasks performed as Teaching Assistant include organizing course materials, designing coding assignments, providing appropriate assistance and evaluating students' performance. The courses he has instructed as Teaching Assistant include:

- Parallel Systems (Graduate)
- Operating Systems (Undergrad)
- Systems Programming (Undergrad)
- Compilers: Principles And Practice (Undergrad)

COURSES TAKEN

Theory Courses:	
Algorithm Design Analytics and Implementation	CS58000
Linear Algebra	MA51100
Numerical Linear Algebra	CS51500
Systems Courses:	
 Compiler & Programming Systems 	CS50200
Operating Systems	CS50300
Parallel Computing	CS52500
Database Systems	CS54100
 Programming Languages 	CS56500
Statistical CS Courses:	
Data Mining	CS57300
Research Seminars:	
Graph Data Management	CS59000
 Fault Tolerant Computer Systems Design 	CS59000
 Language-Based Systems Security 	CS59000
 Computer-aided Program Reasoning 	CS59000
 Deep Learning and System Reasoning 	CS59000
Communication:	
Effective Teaching In CS	CS59100
 Classroom Communication English as a Second Language for TAs 	
ENGL62000	
• Written Communication English as a Second Language Graduates ENGL62100	